Hey folks,
so this is going to be a short tutorial.
It's not even really a tutorial.
It's just kind of me talking about some stuff that
I don't expect you to know or use during this class,
but it kind of extends beyond the quarter where if
we had 15 weeks,
like if we were in the semester system,
or if I was designing curriculum for,
you know,
intermediate creative coding part two,
or maybe I wouldn't even call it advanced,
but maybe special topics in
creative coding.
I would make sure that we spent some
time working on the command line and
building small servers.
And so far, we've been developing for the browser.
And when you code for the browser,
one of the things that's kind of incredible about
it that's really like that I love is that you
know you're writing code that
other people are running on their computers in their browsers,
right?
Like it happens in their browser.
And so you're kind of giving up control over it in a particular way.
And that has a lot of potential and it has a lot of affordances.
But it also has its limitations.
You know, some of those are security based like,
oh,
you know,
it's going to ask permission before it turns on their microphone.
Like,
that's a good thing.
But also,
like,
you're not going to be able to open
certain kinds of network connections,
Willie Nilly,
using somebody else's computer,
you know,
that would,
that would be like,
unless you hacked them,
we're not doing that in this class.
So when you have a server,
or if you're running commands on your own computer,
you have,
you know, there's a lot more you can do.
You can.
and run services,
which is to say
things like web servers,
like other kinds of servers,
you could run infrastructure
that makes web RTC work,
which is like a protocol
for doing real time.
You can kind of like run your own kind of zoom equivalent
in the browser,
and that takes some infrastructure.
You can process media where you know,
you're changing video compression or audio
compression or chopping it up into bits,
and saving the files and making those available on the web.
There's, you know, you can run scrapers, which
you know are loading websites that
have information you want and then
kind of honing in on that and then structuring it usually in JSON
or another formats that you can then use as part of a web app.
Lots of things you can do and it's a
really different set of ontologies.
Like you can you can use JavaScript on the
command line using a system called node.
You could also run Python or Rust or and you know,
their web servers written in a lot of different languages.
And it gives you a lot of flexibility and power in that way,
but it can also be really confusing to know
what to do when you're starting out.
And so I just want to just give you
a sense of a little bit of what that ecosystem looks like right now.
And I can tell you a little bit about what I use and why I use it.
We're going to start with Sam Levine over here.
We've looked at a number of his projects this quarter.
And he has this really nice introduction to the command line.
If you have a Windows machine,
you probably need the Windows Linux
subsystem to do what he's describing here,
which lets you have kind of a virtual Linux
machine as part of your Windows machine.
If you're on a map, you can see that it's a very,
very good one. If you're on a Mac,
then this tutorial will just you can kind of use it as is
because he's on a Mac. And he he'll be using the Mac terminal,
which Mac OS has been built on a variety of
Linux called free BSD for over over 20 years now,
which is,
which is kind of neat.
And there are tools like
home brew that let you install Unix and Linux tools on a Mac.
And I would also say is like,
while it's nice to have your own developer,
developer set up on your own computer so you can test things locally,
I really don't recommend hosting things
on your private computer that has your email and
your private files and your photos and stuff.
It's just,
it's not a great idea.
It's good to have a separation of concerns.
So,
if you want to, you could run a Raspberry Pi.
And use a service like Duck DNS that I'll
talk about in a little bit where it's
actually running a web server from your home.
A lot of people have set up solar powered
servers that are doing this kind of thing.
And you can also, you know, rent.
Cloud server space,
which is going to be a little bit more reliable
than you having to maintain your own hardware.
So,
this is a good introduction to the command line.
And I'm going to be coming back and doing another
tutorial about the kind of scraping that I've done.
Because I think it,
you know,
it's helpful to look at how some of the
things that we've been doing in terms
of using CSS selectors and the DOM, like,
oh,
like what happens when you're trying to
kind of operate on somebody else's code,
somebody else's HTML,
somebody else's structured web stuff in order to get data out of it.
But,
you know,
this,
this gives a good explanation for how to work on the command line,
how to move around and directory is and how to run commands.
So,
I'm going to be able to do a little bit of work on the command line. I, for the most part, developed JavaScript,
both on the server and
on the browser.
And there's something elegant about being able
to use the same language for both concerns,
but node, which is JavaScript on the,
on the command line or on the server really has its own stuff,
it's own learning curve,
like import,
create server from node HTTP,
like, you know, that doesn't look like
how we use JavaScript in the browser.
And import here is bringing in some
functionality from a built-in library,
this node HTTP,
which is native to
kind of when you install node,
you also get the HTTP library,
HTTPS,
you get FS,
which is working with the file system so you can write
files and read files from different to different files.
So,
it's a number you don't need to know,
but just know that there's a lot.
And some of them are used like port 22,
I think,
is used for SSH,
like,
when we connect a terminal to another terminal securely.
Port 80 is used for HTTP, like,
unencrypted web traffic.
And, you know, you use this stuff. You can use it.
And I start to
remember what certain things are,
but when you're setting up web servers,
you know,
you can,
this can run on port 3000,
which would actually require,
you know,
in the URL here.
In order to load something on port 3000,
you use a colon slash before the slash to designate the port.
But you can also use,
like,
a reverse proxy if you run engine X or a patch here,
a web server to,
like,
smooth over that if you run your own domain.
And you're probably going, like,
wait, what?
But just like,
as you're setting these services up,
you also get to,
like,
hook them up to different domains that you own.
You can start hoarding domain names,
which is a good way to set your money on fire,
but also have cool stuff that,
you know,
cool,
cool things that point to projects that you haven't built yet.
I speak from experience.
I have more than I know what to do with.
And I've never released old one for profit.
So,
another part of the
node ecosystem is NPM. And so this is a search for audio.
And there's like a thousand packages.
And,
like,
other parts of the open source ecosystem,
you want to be discerning,
right?
Like,
here are different libraries that you can install using NPM,
the node package manager and use in a server side JavaScript thing.
And there,
you know,
like,
some of these are going to be for doing an
equivalent of web audio on the server side.
Some of these are going to be for transcoding tools.
There's a lot of cool stuff out there.
But you want to look at, oh,
this one was updated eight days ago.
So at least we know that's kind of like
probably actively being developed.
And this one was updated nine years ago.
So like, okay, that's probably been abandoned.
Probably not a lot of community around that one.
And installing node on Mac and the Windows
Linux subsystem or on Linux is not so bad.
I use a tool called NVM. I'll show you in a tab,
but this is kind of what it looks like.
Like, here I've listed all of the
versions of NPM,
a rather of node that are available to download.
And you can actually have multiple at a time on your computer.
And then you just like pick which one
you want to use it to give in time.
Because some of these,
some of these, if
it turned out you really wanted to use one
of these things on NPM from nine years ago,
you would probably have to use it.
And then you can use a version of node from around that time.
Because there have been important changes.
And so you can see like you can install
different versions and use them.
And it's a nice to have a manager that abstracts that for you.
Because if you have conflicting versions,
it can be trouble.
Python is similar now with Venn,
and other like environment variable systems
so that you don't end up with conflicts.
But this is a part of like working on
the server side that can they can eat.
And then you can just do a time up.
So just
don't let that scare you off.
Just,
you know,
anticipate that you're going to spend time
on it if you end up taking this route.
So yeah, NVM,
they have installers,
they have advice for how to do this on windows and Mac and Linux.
Then if you do end up running
a server on something on one of your own computers,
whether it's like a mini PC or like a
Raspberry Pi or something like that.
Duck DNS is a really nice tool for pointing.
It gives you a script that you run on your computer that's like,
Oh,
what's my IP address.
And then it updates a pointer from basically
you can have like whatever you want duck.
Duck DNS .org as your domain.
And then it will you can point at it that way. And that's for projects that don't necessarily need their own fancy domain. That you can run locally.
Raspberry Pi is a great for projects like this.
You know,
you can get a Pi zero with Wi-Fi for
15 bucks or for what a little over 100,
you can get a Pi 5 with 16 gigs of RAM,
which is like.
Yeah,
that's actually a lot a lot of a lot of compute.
And you can definitely run a web server on something like that.
And then there's serverless hosting.
GitHub pages is serverless hosting,
right?
It's taking a get repository and pulling it to a web server.
It takes a few minutes from every pull to update.
That's one of the reasons it's.
We've,
you know,
you have to smash that refresh button
after you've committed your code.
But Versel is a platform that's kind
of similar where you couldn't set up.
Some server side code and it has a free version.
This is,
you know,
again,
considered like a serverless infrastructure.
And then it scales up to like 20 a month.
Cloudflare,
which is a site that,
you know,
has content delivery networks and DDoS protection.
A lot of free infrastructure services.
They also have their own like free level of their infrastructure.
But when,
you know, you start using.
You're spending a service like this or like
Amazon cloud and you're the large cloud providers.
You're spending some of your precious like.
Learning time learning something that's really specific to.
This particular infrastructure.
And so it can be a kind of vendor lock in.
It makes it harder to leave.
To another thing when you feel
dedicated to it because you learned it.
So that's not to say don't do it.
It's just,
you know,
be wary about what you're doing.
You spend your time on me.
I like, I like VPS droplets.
So digital ocean.
I've,
I've hosted projects on a lot of different sites over the years.
I've been doing this since about 2000. And I'm not
getting any sponsorship money from digital ocean.
It's just I've been using their services for 10,
12 years or so.
And they haven't,
they haven't like made my life hell yet.
So starting at about four bucks a
month for half a gig of RAM. And going,
you know,
six bucks for a full gig of RAM. And twice as much transfer.
And two and a half times as much storage.
Going up to quite a bit more than that,
you know,
a hundred bucks a month for what's.
You know, an eight CPU computer.
These are virtual servers and these
run whatever flavor of Linux you want.
You can push a button and it will have a fresh Ubuntu.
And it's not.
It's not all that you can access H into just within seconds,
which is really neat.
You know, it's not running on your computer.
It doesn't have,
you know,
your email and all your cloud connections on it.
And so it is this
thing that like,
okay,
well,
you set up a web server on it.
It gets hacked.
Oh,
well,
I'll just turn it off and start another one.
You know,
you want to be careful about
making backup,
using you can use Git and user repository.
But you can set the server up.
You're away.
And depending on how much memory you have,
you can run some pretty interesting services.
You can have a box that,
you know,
your you drag files on and it converts them to like
the format of the thing that you want.
You can set up, you know,
certain workflows.
You can store files based on,
you know,
something that a website that you set up is doing.
And you can run.
You can run Python on it.
You can run Rust.
You can run Node.
You can, you know, it's.
It's fun to experiment with these things.
And there.
I like that they're low stakes.
You basically pay by the second.
And you can you can launch them and then shut them down.
And it's a few bucks.
So
I don't expect you to be using any of this stuff in
CT 120. But if you want to and you end up using it, you can use it.
You can check the experimenting with this stuff so that you can
add some server side capability to the project that you're doing.
That's finding great.
If you're going to continue using creative code.
In your practice.
Beyond this class,
Into Next Year.
beyond the program.
At some point I recommend experimenting with.
Working on the command line and working on the server because
it does open a lot of possibilities for a couleur project.
your own sense of
what you want to do,
whether it's like running your own server side,
AI
things,
or computer vision,
or listening,
or setting up a file archive, or
whatever it
is.
But yeah,
this is basically some of the
infrastructure you could use to do that.
I will be doing a tutorial around scraping next,
which takes advantage of some of these tools.
And thank you for listening and have a good one.